<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Download Holodeck</title>
    <author>Hamid Ben Malek</author>
  </properties>
  <body>

<div class="section"><h2>Download Holodeck 1.0.1</h2>
 Holodeck 1.0.1 bundles everything to run out-of-the-box: it has tomcat-6.0.20, axis-1.5.1, apache derby,
 and apache ActiveMQ-5.3. You can download the binaries from here:
 <a href="download/holodeck-1.0.1_full.zip"> holodeck-1.0.1_full.zip</a>
 <br/>
 <p>
 To download the latest source code from subversion, issue the following command (this assumes you have installed an SVN
 client on your machine, like "TortoiseSVN" for example): <br/>
  <center><b>svn co https://holodeck-b2b.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/holodeck-b2b holodeck</b></center>
 </p>
</div>

<div class="section"><h3>Previous Releases (version 1.0)</h3>
<p>
Holodeck version 1.0 is distributed in several packages for your convenience. The first package, called &quot;Full Holodeck&quot; consists
of the Holodeck implementation bundled with Axis2-1.4.1, Derby, Tomcat-6.0.20, and ActiveMQ 5.3. 
</p>
<p>
 The second package, called &quot;Holodeck&quot;, contains Axis2, Derby, and Tomcat but does not contain ActiveMQ.
</p>
<p>
The third package, called &quot;Light Holodeck&quot;, contains only Axis2 and Derby and does not contain Tomcat and 
ActiveMQ, and therefore is intended to those users who already have a tomcat instance running on their 
machine and do not want to download another instance of tomcat. 
</p>
<p>
The first two packages (&quot;Full Holodeck&quot; and &quot;Holodeck&quot;) run out-of-the-box. 
The third package would need to be first deployed on Tomcat (or any Servlet Container) before it can run.
</p>
<p>
The last package (holodeck-1.0_src.zip) is the source code of Holodeck</p><p>Holodeck 1.0 is distributed 
under the LGPL license.
</p>
<table class="bodyTable">
  <tbody>
    <tr class="a">
      <td align="left">Package</td>
      <td align="left">Location</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="b">
      <td align="left">Full Holodeck 1.0 (zip)<br />(holodeck + Axis2 + Derby + Tomcat + ActiveMQ)</td>
      <td align="left"><a href="download/holodeck-1.0_full.zip"> holodeck-1.0_full.zip</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="a">
      <td align="left">Holodeck 1.0 (zip)<br />(Holodeck + Axis2 + Derby + Tomcat)</td>
      <td align="left"><a href="download/holodeck-1.0.zip"> holodeck-1.0.zip</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="b">
      <td align="left">Light Holodeck 1.0 (zip)<br />(holodeck + Axix2 + Derby)</td>
      <td align="left"><a href="download/holodeck-1.0_light.zip"> holodeck-1.0_light.zip</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="a">
      <td align="left">Holodeck 1.0 Source (zip)<br />(Holodeck Source Code)</td>
      <td align="left"><a href="download/holodeck-1.0_src.zip"> holodeck-1.0_src.zip</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
</div>

<div class="section"><h3>System <a name="Requirements">Requirements</a></h3>
<table class="bodyTable">
  <tbody>
    <tr class="b">
      <td align="left"><b>JDK</b></td>
      <td align="left">1.6 or above (as of this moment, the latest JDK version is 1.6.0_16). 
          This is mandatory. The user must have this installed on his/her machine. 
          See installation instruction below...</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="a">
      <td align="left"><b>Servlet Container</b></td>
      <td align="left">Holodeck is a J2EE web application and needs a J2EE Servlet Container to run. 
          Any J2EE Server would do the job (Tomcat, JBoss, WebLogic, WebSphere, etc...). 
          We recommend the latest version of Tomcat as it is small in size. 
          The latest version of Tomcat is included in the first two packages 
          (&quot;Full Holodeck&quot; and &quot;Holodeck&quot;) as well as in holodeck 1.0.1.</td>
      </tr>
    <tr class="b">
      <td align="left"><b>ActiveMQ</b></td>
      <td align="left">ActiveMQ (or any JMS Provider of your choice) is an optional component. 
          Use it only if you want Holodeck to communicate with JMS. In Holodeck 1.0, only the first package
          (&quot;Full Holodeck&quot;) includes ActiveMQ. If you are using the second or third 
          package and you also want JMS support, then you can download ActiveMQ separately 
          from http://activemq.apache.org/. If you are using Holodeck 1.0.1, you don't need to
          download ActiveMQ because it runs embedded in the package.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="a">
      <td align="left"><b>Tomcat</b></td>
      <td align="left">Tomcat is already included the first and second package (for holodeck 1.0), as well
          as holodeck 1.0.1. You would need
          to download Tomcat only if you are using the third package of holodeck 1.0 (&quot;Light Holodeck&quot;).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="b">
      <td align="left"><b>Database Server</b></td>
      <td align="left">All Holodeck packages come bundled with apache derby database which is a 
          very fast, scalable and performant database server that can run both as embedded or as a
          server (by default it runs embedded inside holodeck). You have nothing to download to make 
          this work. If however, you prefer to use another relational database server like MySQL, 
          Oracle, etc..., then you would have to install the database server yourself, and then create 
          the database tables from provided scripts (Do not do this unless you don't mind manually 
          configuring things and you know how to play with databases. See instructions below on how 
          to accomplish this...).</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
</div>

<div class="section"><h3><a name="Installation">Installation</a> Instructions</h3>

<p>
  <i>Holodeck is a Java product, so you must have <a href="http://java.sun.com">Java</a> installed in order 
  to proceed. More precisely, you need a Java Development Kit (JDK) 1.6 or later, the Java Runtime 
  Environment (JRE) is not sufficient.</i>
</p>

<div class="section"><h4>Steps</h4>

<ol type="1">
  <li>
    Unzip the distribution archive, i.e. <tt>holodeck-1.0-.zip</tt> to the directory where you wish 
    to install Holodeck 1.0. These instructions assume you chose <tt>D:\Servers\Holodeck-1.0</tt>. 
    The subdirectory <tt>holodeck-1.0</tt> will be created from the archive.
  </li>
  <li>
    If JDK-1.6.20 is not yet installed on your machine, then download it , Add the <tt>JAVA_HOME</tt> 
    environment variable by opening up the system properties (WinKey + Pause), selecting 
    the &quot;Advanced&quot; tab, and the &quot;Environment Variables&quot; button, then adding 
    the <tt>JAVA_HOME</tt> variable in the user variables with the value <tt>D:\Java\jdk-1.6.20</tt> 
    (here we are assuming this is the directory where you installed JDK). If <tt>JAVA_HOME</tt> 
    already exists in your user variables or in the system variables, then you are already set.
  </li>
  <li>
    In the same dialog, make sure that <tt>%JAVA_HOME%\bin</tt> exists in the value of your <tt>PATH</tt> 
    variable.</li><li><b>Optional</b>: Install Tomcat as a windows service. You can do this by issuing the 
    following command from a DOS window: <tt>service install</tt> (this command should be executed from 
    the <tt>Holodeck-1.0\server\bin</tt> directory<p>That's it for the installation.</p>
  </li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>

<div class="section"><h3><a name="Installation">Installation</a> Instructions for using MySQL</h3>

<p>
  The following instructions are only for those users who want to use MySQL database server instead of 
  the apache derby that is bundled with Holodeck. Note that there is no difference between apache derby 
  and MySQL. They are both performant databases (derby is even faster and scalable). The only reason 
  you would prefer MySQL over derby could be because you already have MySQL running in your department 
  and many collegues are using it and you want them to access the database while holodeck is running.
</p>

<ol type="1">
  <li>
    If you don't have MySQL Server already installed, then you can download an installer from Sun from 
    this location <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/get/Downloads/MySQL-5.1/mysql-5.1.31-win32.msi/from/pick#mirrors"> 
    MySQL installer</a>.
  </li>
  <li>
    Assuming that MySQL is well installed and running as a windows service, then you need to create 
    two databases: (a) The first database is called &quot;ebms3&quot; and the user accessing this database 
    is also called &quot;ebms3&quot; (the password is also &quot;ebms3&quot;). If you want to change the 
    name of the database or the username/password, then you will have to also modify the 
    file &quot;Holodeck-1.0\msh\WEB-INF\classes\META-INF\persistence.xml&quot; so that it matches 
    the database name and username/password that you have chosen. (b) The second database you have 
    to create is called &quot;wsrm&quot; (the username/password accessing this database is 
    also &quot;wsrm/wsrm&quot;).</li><li>Once you created the two databases &quot;ebms3&quot; 
    and &quot;wsrm&quot;, then you have to create tables for these databases. Holodeck comes with DDL 
    files (SQL files) that contain SQL script to create the tables for you. You can find those sql scripts 
    in the folder &quot;Holodeck-1.0\store\derby\&quot;: these sql files are called 
    &quot;ebms3-schema-mysql.ddl&quot; and &quot;reliability-schema-mysql.ddl&quot;. Also, if you want 
    Holodeck to use MySQL server, you also need to modify the file 
    &quot;Holodeck-1.0\msh\WEB-INF\modules\holodeck-ebms3\META-INF\module.xml&quot; and modify the 
    value of the parameter called &quot;PersistenceUnit&quot; from &quot;ebms3-derby&quot; 
    to &quot;ebms3-mysql&quot;. Similarly, you would have to do the same to the 
    file &quot;Holodeck-1.0\msh\WEB-INF\modules\holodeck-reliability\META-INF\module.xml&quot;.
  </li>
</ol>
</div>

<div class="section"><h3>Instructions for using another Tomcat Server</h3>

<p>
  These instructions are only for those users who already have tomcat installed on their machine prior 
  to downloading holodeck, and they want to run holodeck on their pre-existing tomcat instance. In this 
  case, you just need to deploy holodeck web application on tomcat (Holodeck web application is the 
  folder &quot;Holodeck-1.0\msh&quot;). To do this, in notepad you create a new file in which you enter 
  the following: </p><p>&lt;Context docBase=&quot;D:/Servers/Holodeck-1.0/msh&quot; 
  reloadable=&quot;true&quot; /&gt;</p><p>and save the file as &quot;holodeck.xml&quot; 
  under your &quot;tomcat/conf/Catalina/localhost&quot; directory. 
  Here we assumed that &quot;Holodeck-1.0&quot; directory is under &quot;D:\Servers&quot; folder. 
  Then you edit the file &quot;D:/Servers/Holodeck-1.0/msh/WEB-INF/classes/META-INF/persistence.xml&quot; 
  and change the sentence &quot;jdbc:derby:../../store/derby/wsrmDB;create=false&quot; to 
  &quot;jdbc:derby:D:/Servers/Holodeck-1.0/store/derby/wsrmDB;create=false&quot;. There are two such 
  sentences in the file (do a search for &quot;jdbc:derby:../../store/derby/wsrmDB;create=false&quot;).
</p>
</div>

<div class="section"><h3><a name="Running">Running</a> Holodeck</h3>

<ol type="1">
  <li>
    Configure the PModes or create new PMode files (See documentation on <a href="pmodes.html"> PModes</a>).
  </li>
  <li>
    Run Holodeck. To run Holodeck you only need to start the J2EE Servlet Container in which Holodeck is 
    deployed. If you are using Tomcat which is bundled with Holodeck, then just start Tomcat by executing 
    the batch file <tt>Holodeck-1.0/server/bin/startup.bat</tt> or by starting the tomcat windows service 
    (if you have installed tomcat as a windows service).</li><li>Submit messages to be sent. 
    See documentation on how to <a href="guides/getting-started/holodeck-in-five-minutes.html">submit messages</a>.
  </li>
</ol>
</div>

</body>
</document>